

## Curriculum Vitae for Diako Darian

### **Personal information**

Address: Tvetenveien 215 E-mail: diako.darian@gmail.com

0675 Oslo Phone: +47 466 93 039

Born: 24.08.1985 Nationality: Norwegian

# **Summary**

I hold a MSc. in Theoretical Physics and I have submitted my Ph.D. in Computational Fluid Mechanics. As a student at both Physics and Mathematics institutes at the University of Oslo, I have acquired a broad knowledge in various physical, mathematical and numerical methods, as well as data science. Within my Ph.D. period I have had the opportunity to work both alone and in team with other researchers from both Norway and several other international universities. In addition, I have had two international research stays (six months in total) at the Kobe University, Japan. The core of my doctoral research was related to the development of high performance numerical codes, utilizing both low level (C/C++) and high level (Python/Cython) languages, to study plasma-object interactions and ionospheric instabilities and turbulence. An important part of my research has been the validation of existing and new mathematical models of plasma-object interactions by means of numerical simulations and comparison with experimental measurements.

### **Technical skills**

Frameworks FEniCS, STL, Boost, MPI, PETSc, NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib

Languages C, C++, Fortran, Java, Python, Cython, Matlab, Mathematica, Bash,

Julia, Rust

Tools Jupyter Notebook, LaTex, Git, GCC, CMake, Linux, OpenFoam, Para-

View

#### **Education**

2014 - 2018 Ph.D. in Mechanics, Department of Mathematics, University of Oslo.

Thesis title 'Plasma-object interactions'.

2008 - 2010	MSc. in Theoretical Physics, Department of Physics, University of
	Oslo
2005 - 2008	BSc. in Physics, Department of Physics, University of Oslo

# **Professional experience**

2019 –	Consultant at Expert Analytics
2014 - 2018	Ph.D. Research Fellow, Department of Mathematics, University of
	Oslo. Including 25% assistant teacher in Calculus, Field Theory and
	Continuum Mechanics.
2006 - 2010	Student mentor to motivate teenagers to choose scientific higher edu-
	cation by offering training in Mathematics and Physics, ENT3R, Fa-
	culty of Mathematics and Natural Sciences, University of Oslo.

# Languages

English	Fluent
Kurdish	Fluent
Norwegian	Fluent
Persian	Fluent
Turkish	Fluent

# Personal skills

Communication	As a result of my Ph.D. research in a multidisciplinary research environment, and teaching duties at the University of Oslo, I have a lot of training in writing and presenting complex methods and technical details to a wide spectrum of audiences with different backgrounds.
Development	I have been involved in developing both high performance codes and writing scripts for data analysis and visualization for both large and small projects. My Ph.D. research reflects my ability to work alone and in teams with people with different background and education.
Management	Through my work with different projects and people I have gained experience in how to design, develop and manage both small and large projects.
Physics,	With a broad background from different fields within Physics and
Mathematics,	Mathematics, I have developed the necessary analytical skills and mindset for approaching complex phenomena and problems. Devel-
Programming	oping new numerical codes, and generating and analyzing large scale simulation data to validate existing and new mathematical models have been a core component of my research.

### Some interests and hobbies

Academic Scientific Computing, Hydrodynamics, Magnetohydrodynamics, Space

and Plasma Physics, Cosmology, Geometric Algebra

Other Powerlifting, Skiing, Hiking, Running

## **Extended descriptions of selected projects**

Activity Implementation of generic velocity distribution functions for modeling

of plasmas.

Period 2018 (October-December)
Role Lead developer and manager

Staffing 2

Volume 80% - 100%

Description This was my final project as a Ph.D. student. During this project, I

extended the Orbital-motion-limited (OML) theory, which describes plasma-object interactions, to non-Maxwellian plasmas. To validate the theory, I had to add a generic functionality to PUNC++ (described below) for handling plasma particles with arbitrary velocity distribution functions. A very good agreement between the theory and numerical

simulations with PUNC++ was achieved.

Tools C++, CMake, GCC, FEniCS, PUNC++, ParaView

Activity PUNC++ - Particle-in-Unstructured-Cell written in C++

Period July 2017 - October 2018

Role Lead developer and co-leader of the project

Staffing 4 Volume 100%

Description In order to be able to run large scale simulations of plasma-object

interactions, a high performance programming code is an absolute necessity. For this reason C++ was chosen as the main programming language for this project. PUNC++ is capable of simulating multiple electrically conducting objects with arbitrary geometries, both floating and connected to other objects in arbitrary circuits. Several finite element solvers with different order of accuracy are also implemented, which can be chosen by the user depending on the desired computa-

tional accuracy and efficiency.

Tools C++, CMake, GCC, FEniCS

Activity PUNC - Particle-in-Unstructured-Cell

Period 2016 (September-December)

Role Co-leader and co-developer of the project

Staffing 4 Volume 100% Description The main goal of this project was a rapid prototyping of a new model

for handling conducting objects with complex geometries in plasmas using the particle-in-cell method within the framework of FEniCS.

Tools Python, FEniCS

Activity Implementation of magnetohydrodynamics equations in SpectraIDNS

Period 2015 (January-December)

Role Lead developer

Staffing 2 Volume 100%

Description Spectral DNS is a high-performance pseudo-spectral Navier-Stokes

DNS solver developed by Mikael Mortensen. My contribution to this project is the implementation of magnetohydrodynamics solvers to

study plasma instabilities and turbulence in the ionosphere.

Tools Python, Cython, ParaView